<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" version="2.0">
	<channel>
		<title />
		<link>/</link>
		<description />
		<copyright>Copyright © 2023</copyright>
		<pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 03:27:20 GMT</pubDate>
		<lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 03:27:20 GMT</lastBuildDate>
		<item>
			<title>Invincibility in Mario Kart 8 Deluxe</title>
			<link>/posts/invincibility-stat</link>
			<description>How to calculate invincibility time for your combination</description>
			<enclosure url="/images/bg/bwp.jpg" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid isPermaLink="false">/posts/invincibility-stat</guid>
			<pubDate>Thu, 25 May 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In version 2.2.0, Nintendo introduced a new hidden stat to Mario Kart 8 Deluxe, Invincibility, which controls how long you will be invincible for after you have gotten hit.
In this blog post I will walk through how you can see this stat, how that stat value maps to a scaling factor, and how you can use the scaling factor to calculate exactly how long the invincibility time will be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The majority of the information and numbers in this guide come from the &lt;a href="http://japan-mk.blog.jp/mk8dx.info-1"&gt;Mario Kart Blog&lt;/a&gt; and it would not be possible without their work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="seeing-your-invincibility-stat"&gt;Seeing your invincibility stat&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To find your invincibility stat, you will need to use a combo builder website and fill in your combination.
Two such sites are &lt;a href="https://mk8dxbuilder.com/"&gt;mk8dxbuilder.com&lt;/a&gt; or the &lt;a href="/tools/mk8dx-combo-finder"&gt;combo finder&lt;/a&gt; on my site.
The stat value should be a number between 1 and 5.75.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, the combination Yoshi / Inkstriker / Roller / Cloud Glider has an invincibility stat of 2.25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-it-gets-converted-to-in-game-invincibility-time"&gt;How it gets converted to in-game invincibility time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you get hit, you are stopped and unable to move for a short period of time, then you are able to start driving again and the invincibility time (also known as invincibility frames or i-frames) will start.
The duration of time you are unable to move, and the duration you are invincible depends on what you were hit by. Below is a table showing how many frames each component takes for each damage source. Durations are given in a number of frames which can be converted to seconds by dividing by 60 as Mario Kart 8 Deluxe runs at 60 frames per second.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="row justify-content-center"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-auto"&gt;
&lt;!--?# Table Class="table table-striped table-bordered table-sm table-hover text-center table-responsive" HeaderRows=1 ?--&gt;
&lt;!--?*
"Damage Source" "Stopped Frames" "Invincibility Frames"
"Green Shell, Red Shell" 90 91     
"Banana, Blue Shell, Bob-omb" 90 90     
Lightning 60 90     
"Boomerang Flower" 65 57     
"Bullet Bill, Super Horn" 65 56     
"Fire Flower" 63 56     
"Star, Piranha Plant, Other" 60 60     
?--&gt;
&lt;!--?#/ Table ?--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The invincibility stat works by scaling up or down the number of invincibility frames and does not affect the number of stopped frames.
To calculate how much it gets scaled by, you need to find the scaling factor using the following table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="row justify-content-center"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-auto"&gt;
&lt;!--?# Table Class="table table-striped table-bordered table-sm table-hover text-center table-responsive" HeaderRows=1 ?--&gt;
&lt;!--?*
"Invincibility Stat" "Scaling Factor"
1.00 0.65     
1.25 0.67     
1.50 0.70     
1.75 0.74     
2.00 0.79     
2.25 0.85     
2.50 0.91     
2.75 0.97     
3.00 1.03     
3.25 1.09     
3.50 1.15     
3.75 1.20     
4.00 1.25     
4.25 1.29     
4.50 1.33     
4.75 1.37     
5.00 1.41     
5.25 1.44     
5.50 1.47     
5.75 1.50     
?--&gt;
&lt;!--?#/ Table ?--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have the scaling factor, you can multiply it by the number of invincibility frames to get the actual number of invincibility frames you will experience in-game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-worked-example"&gt;A worked example&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example, let's say that you are using Yoshi / Inkstriker / Roller / Cloud Glider and have just hit a banana.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We know that the invincibility stat is 2.25, and using the table we can get a scaling factor of 0.85.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting hit by a banana will stop you for 90 frames (1.5 seconds), and will then have a further 90 frames (1.5 seconds) of invincibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We multiply the 90 frames of invincibility by 0.85 to get the correct invincibility frame count of ~77 frames (1.28 seconds).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In total, you will be stopped or invincible for 167 frames (2.78 seconds).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="some-more-examples-to-compare"&gt;Some more examples to compare&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="row justify-content-center"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-auto"&gt;
&lt;!--?# Table Class="table table-striped table-bordered table-sm table-hover text-center table-responsive" HeaderRows=1 ?--&gt;
&lt;!--?*
Combination "Invincibility Stat" "Damage Source" "Stopped Duration" "Invincibility Duration" "Total Duration"
"Yoshi / Inkstriker / Roller / Cloud" 2.25 Banana "90F / 1.5s" "77F / 1.28s" "167F / 2.78s"     
"Yoshi / Teddy Buggy / Button / Cloud" 2.75 Banana "90F / 1.5s" "87F / 1.45s" "177F / 2.95s"     
"Yoshi / Teddy Buggy / GLA / Cloud" 3.25 Banana "90F / 1.5s" "98F / 1.63s" "188F / 3.13s"     
"Yoshi / Inkstriker / Roller / Cloud" 2.25 Star "60F / 1s" "51F / 0.85s" "111F / 1.85s"     
"Yoshi / Teddy Buggy / Button / Cloud" 2.75 Star "60F / 1s" "58F / 0.97s" "118F / 1.97s"     
"Yoshi / Teddy Buggy / GLA / Cloud" 3.25 Star "60F / 1s" "65F / 1.08s" "125F / 2.08s"     
?--&gt;
&lt;!--?#/ Table ?--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-much-invincibility-do-i-need"&gt;How much invincibility do I need?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a much harder question to answer and it really comes down to each individual and their playstyle.
My blog post on &lt;a href="/posts/mk8dx-combos"&gt;choosing your combination&lt;/a&gt; goes into more details about how to choose your combination and weigh it against the other stats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an example of why playstyle matters, imagine a situation where you are in first place and you currently have two protective items, but you really want to get a super horn as you think a blue shell may come soon.
Having higher invincibility makes throwing away those two protective items slightly less risky since the person behind you will have to space out red shells more to hit you twice, and it is more likely they will fail to space it apart enough and waste a red shell.
If you are a more risk-averse player who would instead prefer to hold those two protective items, then maybe you won't benefit as much from that additional invincibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A 0.25 increase in invincibility stat is not very noticeable, but a 1.00 increase in invincibility stat is much more noticeable with you getting around 0.35 seconds extra invincibility when hit by a banana and 0.23 seconds extra invincibility when hit by a star.
It is easy to think of scenarios where having an extra 0.35 seconds of invincibility could get you a much better position at the end of the race.
Increasing your invincibility stat will usually come at the cost of some other stat values, so you will need to weight those costs against the benefits when choosing your combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GLA Tires seems to be a popular choice at the moment for getting significantly more invincibility, however it does come at the cost of 0.5 MT.
Leaf and Button tires also are good options for getting a bit more invincibility while only sacrificing 0.25 MT.
Cushion and Sponge tires also have very good invincibility, but from my experience they seem to be very bouncy and that impacts driving lines a lot where it may not be a viable choice, but I would encourage you to try it out and form your own opinion.
If after all this, you think that the invincibility stat seems like it has too little impact to be useful, then sticking with Roller tires will be the best option.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
			<comments xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">0</comments>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Choosing your combination in Mario Kart 8 Deluxe</title>
			<link>/posts/mk8dx-combos</link>
			<description>What the balance changes in version 2.3.0 mean for you</description>
			<enclosure url="/images/bg/byi.png" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid isPermaLink="false">/posts/mk8dx-combos</guid>
			<pubDate>Fri, 10 Mar 2023 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Version 2.3.0 of Mario Kart 8 Deluxe was released on March 9th, 2023.
With this change came wave 4 of the Booster Course Pass including 8 new tracks, a new playable character, and a sleuth of statistic changes to characters, vehicle bodies, and tires.
This post will cover all the changes that were made, some discussion about what each of the stats actually mean, and how you can use that to choose the combination you will use online.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="what-changed"&gt;What changed?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common criticism of Mario Kart 8 Deluxe is that if you were to play online you would be facing a room full of Waluigis.
Before 2.3.0, Waluigi was by far the best character to use online because it allowed you to have a good balance of speed, weight, and acceleration.
Over the last three waves of the Booster Course Pass, Nintendo has made significant balance changes which appear to have been done to address this criticism and level the playing field.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In version 2.1.0, Nintendo made it so that having a larger weight was not as significant as it was before.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In version 2.2.0, Nintendo added a new statistic that changed the time that you are invincible from damage after being hit. The worst invincibility value was given to Waluigi.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In version 2.3.0, Nintendo increased the speed and mini-turbo stats of various characters, vehicle bodies, and tires by 0.25.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The changes in version 2.3.0 were the most significant and were enough to mean that Waluigi is no longer the best character to use.
Because these buffs affect three different aspects of a combination, it means that some combinations have gotten much better.
Someone using Mario, Standard Kart, and Standard Tires has now gotten an additional 0.25 Speed and 0.75 Mini-Turbo with this update.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is a brief summary of all the buffs that were made:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All characters &lt;strong&gt;except&lt;/strong&gt; Waluigi, Donkey Kong, Roy, Wario, Dry Bowser, Metal Mario, Pink Gold Peach, Bowser, Morton, and Mii (Heavy) received +0.25 Speed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Baby Mario, Baby Luigi, Dry Bones, Mii (Light), Toad, Shy Guy, Larry, Peach, Daisy, Yoshi, Mario, Ludwig, Mii (Medium), Luigi, and Iggy all received +0.25 Mini-Turbo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All bodies &lt;strong&gt;except&lt;/strong&gt; Pipe Frame, Varmint, City Tripper, Biddybuggy, Mr. Scooty, Landship, Streetle, W 25 Silver Arrow, Standard Bike, Flame Rider, and Wild Wiggler received +0.25 Mini-Turbo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All tires &lt;strong&gt;except&lt;/strong&gt; Roller, Azure Roller, Button, and Leaf received +0.25 Mini-Turbo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the parts that received buffs were ones that were not commonly used when playing online, and with these stat increases there are many more viable combinations that can be used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="what-do-the-stats-mean"&gt;What do the stats mean?&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To help with explaining how to choose your combination, below is a summary of each statistic type and how it translates to gameplay.
Each statistic has a value between 0.75 to 5.75, and can be viewed in-game by pressing the plus button when selecting your vehicle.
Some of the statistics are not viewable in-game such as Mini-Turbo, Invincibility, and the Air, Water, and Anti-Gravity parts of the speed and handling stats.
To see these hidden statistics you can use a site such as &lt;a href="https://mk8dxbuilder.com/"&gt;mk8dxbuilder.com&lt;/a&gt; or my &lt;a href="/tools/mk8dx-combo-finder"&gt;MK8DX Combo Finder Tool&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="speed"&gt;Speed&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speed is the top speed that you can reach. It also affects your speed when in a mushroom or a mini-turbo.
Each combination has 4 speed stats: Ground, Air, Water, and Anti-Gravity which affect your top speed in each of those conditions.
When you are not at your top speed, the speed stat has no impact and instead your current speed will be determined solely by your acceleration.
Turning in Mario Kart reduces your speed, which means that the more turns a track has, the less relevant the speed stat is.
If you are using a character with low speed, you can overcome the speed limitations by maximising the amount of time you are in a mini-turbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="acceleration"&gt;Acceleration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Acceleration affects how quickly your speed increases.
When you are at your top speed, acceleration has no impact.
For the same reason, using a mushroom, entering a mini-turbo, or being in a star also means acceleration has no impact.
If you are using a character with low acceleration, you will want to do very simple lines and drive straight as often as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="weight"&gt;Weight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Weight affects how far you get pushed away when bumping into another player.
Weight has no impact on time trials but is important in online play as bumps can be quite severe and cause you to miss item boxes or be pushed off the track.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="handling"&gt;Handling&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Handling affects how fast you can turn.
While drifting this changes how tight or wide you can make your drift.
Just like the speed stat, handling is also represented using 4 different stats: Ground, Air, Water, and Anti-Gravity which affect your handling in each of those conditions.
Having higher handling is very useful for online play where you need to be able to adapt to all sorts of scenarios such as adjusting your drift to avoid an item.
It is also useful in TTs for tracks which have tight or wide turns.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="traction"&gt;Traction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traction affects how much you slip on tracks with ice or sand on the road.
This includes the ice on tracks like Sherbet Land and Snow Land, and the sand on Dry Dry Desert and Donut Plains.
For tracks that have no ice or sand, traction has no effect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="mini-turbo"&gt;Mini-Turbo&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mini-Turbo affects how quickly you are able to build up mini-turbos, and how long they last once you release them.
For more information about how to calculate the time needed to accumulate an MT, refer to my &lt;a href="/drifting-guide#mt-accumulation"&gt;drifting guide&lt;/a&gt; which goes into more detail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="invincibility"&gt;Invincibility&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Invincibility controls the amount of time you are invincible after getting hit by something.
This has no impact on time trials, but can be useful in online play.
As an example, if you were hit by a bomb, then an invincibility stat of 1 means you will be invincible for 0.97 seconds after recovering, while an invincibility stat of 5.75 will be invincible for 2.25 seconds after recovering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="other-differences"&gt;Other differences&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from stats, there are a few other things that separate different combinations apart from each other:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hitbox
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The hitbox of a combination can vary even if they have identical stats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a larger hitbox means you don't have to drift as wide to get a coin and you can hang more over an edge without falling off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Having a smaller hitbox means you can avoid items easier and you can get closer to a wall without bumping it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Drifting Style
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every vehicle body is one of 4 types: Kart (e.g. Biddybuggy), Standard Bike (e.g. Mr. Scooty), Sport Bike (e.g. Yoshi Bike), and ATV (e.g. Wild Wiggler).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Sport bikes (commonly known as inward bikes) are the most notably different, however the other three types have very subtle differences in how they drift.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The differences between the outward drifting vehicle types are difficult to explain, but their turning circles when drifting vary slightly.
Standard bikes have the most noticeable difference as when you start a drift it tends to go out very wide compared to karts and ATVs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Popularity
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are playing in a competitive match in a team, you will want to identify easily which players are on your team and which players are not. If everyone is using the same character, then you can only do this by communicating with your team in a call or by keeping track of all the player names around you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are playing as a character that no-one else is playing as, then it means all the people on the other teams can easily tell you are an enemy, but it also means that your teammates can easily tell who you are and can see where you are on the mini-map which can be useful when figuring out when to use lightning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ground-anti-gravity-air-and-water-components"&gt;Ground, Anti-Gravity, Air, and Water components&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speed and handling is split into four components based on the terrain you are driving on.
I &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/1idLq3OYkEjRI0U64LCLxVY-GvdhRPgO75KZUPS4m70o/edit#gid=0"&gt;calculated&lt;/a&gt; the percentage of time across all tracks that is spent driving on each type of terrain and came up with the following distribution:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ground: 72.5%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anti-Gravity: 19.5%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Air: 5.7%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Water: 2.3%&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What this tells us is that ground is the most important stat to look at, followed by anti-gravity, while air and water have very little importance and it means you can safely ignore those stats unless you know you are playing on a track with lots of air time and lots of underwater driving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that if the underwater driving is on an anti-gravity section, the anti-gravity component of the stat takes precedence.
This means that tracks like Water Park do not take advantage of the water component at all, despite most of the track being underwater.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id="how-to-choose-a-combination"&gt;How to choose a combination&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rather than choosing one combination and sticking with it, your combination should change and evolve over time according to your playstyle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are getting bumped around too much, try a combination with higher weight.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are struggling to get the mini-turbos you want, try a combination with higher mini-turbo.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you are doing better on tracks that have lots of turns and worse on tracks that have less turns, try a combination with higher speed and less acceleration.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you find that you are getting hit by too many items and struggle to catch up, use a combination with higher acceleration or invincibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you make these kinds of changes, you are going to have to make a trade-off and get a worse stat in some other place.
If you want more speed, you will likely have to sacrifice your acceleration.
Experiment using time trials and online play to see if these sacrifices are worth it.
Sometimes to use a combination that has higher acceleration and lower speed, you need to learn new lines to take advantage of that.
To learn new lines, I would recommend reading my &lt;a href="/posts/learning-lines"&gt;blog post on how to learn lines&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="how-to-find-new-combinations-to-experiment-with"&gt;How to find new combinations to experiment with&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing that you want more of a stat is one thing, but finding such a combination while minimising the number of sacrifices you have to make is much harder.
Currently there are 43 characters (with 5 more on the way), 41 vehicle bodies, 22 tires, and 15 gliders to choose from meaning 649,440 possible combinations to choose from.
Trying every one of these combinations is impractical, so I have made a &lt;a href="/tools/mk8dx-combo-finder"&gt;tool&lt;/a&gt; that lets you search for combinations with the stats that you want.
The tool is a table of all the combinations and their values, and each column has filter options to help with finding the combination with the statistics you want.
You can also download the data as a CSV to explore it using Excel or Google Sheets if you prefer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run a quick example, say that you are currently using Waluigi, Wild Wiggler, Roller, and Cloud Glider and you want something with more acceleration, and you are willing to sacrifice some speed and weight to get it.
We know this combination has a speed of 3.5, acceleration of 4.25, and a weight of 3.
Using the tool, we can find all combinations with an acceleration ≥ 4.5, speed ≥ 3.25, and weight ≥ 2.75.
After applying these filters, we can see there are 16 combinations that fit the criteria which we can look through and choose the best one.
If we don't like these options, then we know we need to sacrifice more and we could change it to show all combinations with speed ≥ 3 instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-are-some-good-combinations-to-try-out"&gt;What are some good combinations to try out?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below you can find some good example combinations to try out.
For each combination, Roller and Cloud Glider is used as they generally provide the best statistics, but Leaf Tires and Plane Glider are worth trying out as well.
The table is sorted in descending order by acceleration.
You should choose the combination by how much you balance acceleration and mini-turbo against speed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are new to the game and are not sure which to try out first, Luigi with Biddybuggy would be a good starting place.
Waluigi with Wild Wiggler is included in the table for reference, however it is mostly outclassed by Waluigi with Teddy Buggy, so that would be a good first combination to try while experimenting if that is what you used previously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="row justify-content-center"&gt;
&lt;div class="col-auto"&gt;
&lt;!--?# Table Class="table table-striped table-sm table-hover text-center table-responsive" HeaderRows=1 ?--&gt;
&lt;!--?*
Character Body Acceleration Mini-Turbo Speed Handling
"Baby Mario / Baby Luigi / Dry Bones / Mii (Light)" Biddybuggy 5.75 5.75 1.25 5.25
"Toadette / Wendy / Isabelle" Biddybuggy 5.75 5.5 1.5 5
"Toad / Shy Guy / Larry" Biddybuggy 5.5 5.5 1.75 5
"Cat Peach / Inkling Girl / Villager (F)" Biddybuggy 5.5 5.25 2 4.75
"Peach / Daisy / Yoshi / Birdo" Biddybuggy 5.25 5.5 2.25 4.5
"Luigi / Iggy" Biddybuggy 5 5.25 2.5 4.5
"Peach / Daisy / Yoshi / Birdo" "Teddy Buggy" 4.75 5.25 2.75 4.25
"Waluigi / Donkey Kong / Roy" Biddybuggy 4.75 4.75 3 3.75
"Luigi / Iggy" "Teddy Buggy" 4.5 5 3 4.25
"Wario / Dry Bowser" Biddybuggy 4.5 4.5 3.25 3.5
"Rosalina / King Boo / Link" "Teddy Buggy" 4.25 4.75 3.25 3.75
"Waluigi / Donkey Kong / Roy" "Teddy Buggy" 4.25 4.5 3.5 3.5
"Waluigi / Donkey Kong / Roy" "Wild Wiggler" 4.25 4.25 3.5 3.5
?--&gt;
&lt;!--?#/ Table ?--&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content:encoded>
			<comments xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">0</comments>
		</item>
		<item>
			<title>Learning Lines in Mario Kart 8 Deluxe</title>
			<link>/posts/learning-lines</link>
			<description>A comparison of various strategies to learning your lines</description>
			<enclosure url="/images/bg/drr.png" length="0" type="image" />
			<guid isPermaLink="false">/posts/learning-lines</guid>
			<pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
			<content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;I am a strong believer that time trials are a great way for people to improve in competitive Mario Kart 8 Deluxe, and I have spent hundreds of hours practicing my lines in time trial mode.
If a new player who is starting out is asking me for advice on what they can do to get better, I always tell them that improving your lines is a great way to get ahead of your competition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="so-how-do-i-improve-my-lines"&gt;So how do I improve my lines?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I want to improve my skills on a certain track to benefit me in competitive play, I typically watch the world record for the track on &lt;a href="https://www.mkwrs.com/"&gt;mkwrs.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are three drawbacks to using this approach:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The WR uses mushrooms and you want to know what strategies to use when you have no mushrooms&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The WR uses a different combination and has lines that are not possible to take with what you use online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The WR uses techniques which are too inconsistent or risky to be used online&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4 id="shroomless-time-trials-nita"&gt;Shroomless Time Trials (NITA)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address the first of these problems I created a &lt;a href="https://bit.ly/AlternateTTs"&gt;leaderboard&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/9jc88HW"&gt;discord server&lt;/a&gt; to keep track of the fastest shroomless times for each track.
Shroomless time trials are very popular amongst the Japanese community and they commonly refer to them using the acronym &amp;quot;NITA&amp;quot; (No-Item Time Attack).
All submissions to this leaderboard must have video proof, and so it is a great reference for people who want to study shroomless lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To take the most advantage of this, I would recommend creating a new profile on your switch which is used specifically for shroomless time trials with the combination you use online, that way you don't have to worry about deleting any ghosts you have which use shrooms or a different combination.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="shroomless-time-trials-per-combination"&gt;Shroomless Time Trials per Combination&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address the second of these problems, Jet, who is also an admin of the NITA leaderboard, created a &lt;a href="https://bit.ly/3CtE0Ee"&gt;leaderboard&lt;/a&gt; for shroomless time trials that uses Waluigi and Wild Wiggler.
This is a very common combination for competitive play, and if you are someone who uses this combination I would recommend checking out the top times on this leaderboard if you want to improve your lines.
But again, this still suffers from the last problem in which some of the strategies used by the top times are too risky to be used online.
It also doesn't help if you don't use Waluigi Wiggler since I am not aware of any leaderboards for other combinations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="no-item-speedruns"&gt;No Item Speedruns&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address all of these problems, I would recommend watching (and doing) no-item speedruns. This solves the third problem because if a strategy is too risky to be used online it is likely to be too risky for a speedrun.
Speedruns for Mario Kart 8 Deluxe are tracked on &lt;a href="https://www.speedrun.com/mk8dx#48_Tracks"&gt;speedrun.com&lt;/a&gt; and recently we have been seeing more competitive players trying out speedruns.
Speedruns must be done in VS Race mode and you can either speedrun individual cups, 16 tracks, or all 48 tracks in one go.
The more tracks in the speedrun, the less likely it is that the run will contain inconsistent or risky strategies, so I personally prefer the 48 tracks category for practice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But speedruns have another drawback which makes them less popular, loading times. If you have the cartridge version of the game, you will lose over 1 second for each track in loading times compared to those who have a digital copy of the game.
In addition, we have seen that some people will have large loading time differences even if they are both using digital, and large loading time differences between two runs on the same switch. This means that even if you played a track perfectly you may still lose time because your load took 300ms longer than your PB.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently the speedrun staff have been retiming the top runs for each category by excluding loading times, but it is a very manual process and takes too much time, and it doesn't help if you are trying to improve your own times since you are unlikely to do all the work of removing loading times from your own runs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="shroomless-time-trial-speedruns"&gt;Shroomless Time Trial Speedruns&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Over a year ago a new speedrun category called &lt;a href="https://www.speedrun.com/mk8dxce#Time_Trials"&gt;Time Trials&lt;/a&gt; was added. There are categories for shrooms and shroomless, but I would recommend doing the shroomless category if you want to improve your lines.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this category you must use the same combination for every track, you must do the tracks in order, and you only have one attempt at each track. The time at the end is the sum of all the individual time trials.
This takes all the benefits of speedruns and removes the drawback of loading times since they aren't included in the total time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you open the category rules on the speedrun.com page it has instructions for setting up LiveSplit to manually enter the TT times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately there is a drawback to time trial speedruns, and that is that barely anyone has done them.
And with this blog post I hope it might be enough to convince people to give shroomless time trial speedruns a go.&lt;/p&gt;
</content:encoded>
			<comments xmlns="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/">0</comments>
		</item>
	</channel>
</rss>